so i had uh had some really good
questions
from the last video that i did
around listening listening to the logos
and
it was basically on my last to summarize
the last video i talked about how
we don't listen to the logos
we hear it we respond to it
on some level we probably
we probably live in its measure
and it in its products its results but
we don't necessarily have a listening
for the whole the non-contingent
wholeness of the logos right
and the more that that happens we don't
well the more than that happens the more
our lives become a pure kind of
contingency
right it's like i'm doing something as a
means
to produce an outcome or an effect which
will become the next
means or thing that i need to
produce an outcome and an effect
and there's a way in which we can kind
of like like
we can basically our whole lives can
become a pure contingency
right
so let's not do that
easier said than done because
we don't hear that
we're not listening and because we've
lost
sight right of
that we're listening that we have a
listening
i think we end up just only hearing the
products
of the logos and not the living dynamic
the principle of principles right
they're not
like being in its non-contingency right
it's luminosity it's suchness it's
moreness
so one of the questions there were two
questions one was um
that somebody asked was they're like
great let's listen
greed we don't listen but challenge how
do you encourage somebody
to listen who
is it doesn't hear that they're
listening therefore doesn't even know to
ask the question on how to listen
basically is what i heard and the other
one was
um where do you listen from
that was another person i just saw it in
my maybe there was more to it but i
that i only just saw it on my walk over
here so
i just wanted to respond to both of
those
so i think what we can i i really like
those questions
um it's having me think
about it so hear my thoughts about that
so
it's interesting because in regards
to how do we encourage someone
to listen
to that they're not listening
because listening really isn't possible
until we can hear that we're not
listening and the moment we
it's revealed to us we're not listening
is probably the first time
perhaps in our lives that we actually
listen
so how do we do that right
well it's interesting to when you think
about it right
if we ask ourselves
when i deeply listen to somebody
they're speaking and they're telling me
about their lives or they're
telling me what they think and
they're revealing to what whatever depth
they're revealing about whatever it is
that they think or feel or
experiencing when i listen what am i
actually hearing
what am i listening to
well i have i would have to say that if
we say that listening
right if if listening is what all
speech is in a response to
we'd have to say that speaking
it doesn't make any sense until there's
a listening
there must have been something that
called forth something
something like speech
so when we listen to another speech and
we really listen to it
i think what we hear and what they can
maybe
hear us hearing is what they're in
response to
i think that's what happens a lot when
somebody says they feel deeply
seen or deeply godly
it's it's not so much that
i feel like you heard or saw the
attributes of myself
or that that you even heard what i think
to myself
but it's more like you heard
the world in which i'm already always
responding to
and that there's a way i hear it and
thus
my speaking is a response to it so when
i hear you and i get you and i deeply
listen to you
on some level i am
in my response i'm actually revealing
you're listening
and i think so in a strange way i guess
maybe the answer to that question is to
to how do we encourage someone to hear
that they're not listening i think it's
to deeply listen to them
and now to the question and this and i'm
sure they'll end up being related
oftentimes i you know when i start a
sentence
i think i know what i'm going to say and
by the end like i'll start the sentence
by the end of it
i'll realize i have no idea what i was
trying to say
so we'll see if that's the case or not
in this way
so where do i hear from or where is
listening happen
from
it's a great question
[Music]
in some sense right it's kind of a
similar question of
you know when if i ask myself right what
is
what will it take to really attend to
the world in front of me especially if
the world in front of me calls
forth a quality of attention i don't
currently have
yet i feel called in
to pay attention or to listen
or to understand
but yet i don't have the capacity to
understand
yet so how do i
how do i become worthy
of the kind of understanding for which i
don't have yet to be able to understand
well if that wasn't possible on some
level i don't think we would understand
anything
right so i think really the question is
right where does the listening happen
from i think the listening
happens from something like the future
in a in the future
you could say
the future you could say
seizes my attention seizes my hearing
and so i comport myself
to it yet i realize that
i'm not somebody worthy of that
understanding
however in attuning to it
as it reveals itself it folds back i
believe
and attunes me to it
and there's a mutual disclosure that
happens at the
at the edge or the horizon of our own
intelligibility
right
i think we could say that the where
from which listening comes from i
believe
it's in the world right and it's
precisely
in the world in which calls to my
the horizon or what's beyond the horizon
which gives the ground is the ground
upon which i step
forward realizing that
i don't know what i'm looking at yet i
feel
attuned to it and detoned by it
in that mutual self-disclosure
i think is a a very very deep
almost hermenetic
way of